<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.6">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://www.extraordinarylives.us/https://www.extraordinarylives.us/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://www.extraordinarylives.us/https://www.extraordinarylives.us/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-04-25T15:44:39-07:00</updated><id>https://www.extraordinarylives.us/https://www.extraordinarylives.us/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Extraordinary Lives Foundation</title><subtitle>The Extraordinary Lives Foundation is changing the way people think about children's mental health.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">We Fear Odd &amp;amp; Abnormal Behavior</title><link href="https://www.extraordinarylives.us/https://www.extraordinarylives.us/blog/articles/we-fear-odd-and-abnormal-behavior" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="We Fear Odd &amp; Abnormal Behavior" /><published>2019-07-09T19:10:39-07:00</published><updated>2019-07-09T19:10:39-07:00</updated><id>https://www.extraordinarylives.us/https://www.extraordinarylives.us/blog/articles/we-fear-odd-and-abnormal-behavior</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.extraordinarylives.us/https://www.extraordinarylives.us/blog/articles/we-fear-odd-and-abnormal-behavior">&lt;p&gt;If we are honest, most of us initially feel awkward and anxious when confronted with odd and abnormal behavior. You would think doctors would feel differently, but Kenneth James M.D. candidly admits that he found interaction with psychiatric patients uncomfortable and fear inducing. Dr. James is a board certified Obstetrician and Gynecologist who is married to Mara James, the founder of the Extraordinary Lives Foundation and sits on the Advisory Board.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He expresses his fears and feelings on mental health and recounts how experiencing his wife’s personal struggle has made him more understanding and compassionate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“May is Mental Health Awareness month. Five years ago this month my life turned upside down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I was in medical school, I spent 2 months doing a psychiatric rotation at a V.A. Hospital. This was a requirement. I had no interest in psychiatry and honestly never even thought about mental health disorders before medical school, especially during the first 2 years of school. Sure, I learned about the disorders, neurological pathways, possible causes and pharmacologic treatments but I thought of it as a fiction novel not real disorders that happen to real people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My rotation was during a frigid winter at the V.A. Hospital in Chicago. We were introduced to the in-patient ward staff, instructed on areas to go to and avoid and then assigned our patients to follow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remember sitting in my first interview with an inpatient. When I arrived at the physician’s consultation room, the patient was already there sitting opposite the doctor. The patient had schizophrenia and was heavily medicated. He seemed harmless, cooperative and sedated. The session lasted 30 minutes with lots of questions about his medical progress, relationship with other patients, satisfaction with his accommodations and goals to accomplish. When we were done, I stood up to say goodbye and open the door for him. When he stood up, I realized he was over 6 feet 10 inches tall and towered over me like a giant. I immediately went into fight or flight mode. I started sweating, was anxious, nervous, fearful and terrified all at the same time. I felt threatened that he was going to lash out at me. There was no basis for this fear. This was a fantasy I immediately fabricated in my mind from watching too many horror movies in the 70’s. He politely grunted goodbye and was escorted back to the common area by a hospital orderly. It was at this exact moment that I realized I would either fear these patients or learn compassion. I chose fear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the rotation continued, I found myself (and my fellow students) spending more time in the V.A. gymnasium playing basketball than seeing patients. We would study diseases and treatments over breakfast, then play hoops for 2 hours, then lunch and home. I knew the names of all the diseases, symptoms, possible causes and treatment options; I just couldn’t put a face to each disorder because I was afraid of being with people who were psychologically different, diseased or afflicted. Bipolar, schizophrenia, multiple personality disorders and PTSD were cool to talk about and learn the medications that control the symptoms, but to see a person express these disorders live frightened me. Therefore, I avoided patient care for the remainder of my rotation. Sad, but true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My experience in medical school, where it was a requirement to see and interact with psychiatric patients is not that different from any of us who interact with friends, family, neighbors, work mates or strangers who have similar emotional or diagnosed psychiatric conditions. At first it is frightening and uncomfortable. How can someone be there physically but not there mentally or emotionally? It takes time to adjust to and tolerate people with mania, narcissism, or dissociative behavior and to see the real person underneath the disorder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In May of 2014, my wife Mara of over 20 years experienced a manic episode. Looking back, I should have seen it coming like a dark rain cloud before the storm but mostly I just accepted her increasingly bizarre behavior as eccentric. She always had a type A, outgoing and friendly personality. She has always had a lot of friends, been extremely cordial to everyone and made everyone in her presence feel loved and wanted. As her mania slowly progressed, I noticed that many of her friends were not around. Maybe they were growing weary of her changing personality and possibly frightened by her overly talkative behavior and odd mannerisms. Her obsessions with objects, people, and certain situations were bordering on psychiatric and then BAM!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was away the weekend of May 23, 2014 with my parents and brother at a retreat in Colorado. It was one of the few times I had gone away without her. The first night I was gone, she reached the pinnacle of her disease and by the next day I was on a plane home. At 8 pm we embraced. I didn’t want to let her go because I would then have to make some very difficult decisions. With the help of a dear friend who is a psychologist, we decided that she should see her psychologist and a psychiatrist the next day and we would hopefully be able to keep her from being admitted to an inpatient setting. Luckily, with the help of her providers, she was started on medication and started to heal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the next 6 months she underwent her own type of transformation. As she proclaims: ‘I went from medication to meditation’. She finished a short course of medications and therapy and then started alternative treatments. Between hypnotherapy, crystals, shamans, yoga, meditation and religious counseling she was transformed. She is back and better than ever!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mara took her experience and decided to help others. She started a mental health awareness foundation called Extraordinary Lives Foundation (ELF) in 2016. The mission of the foundation is to raise awareness around mental health issues concentrating on children and adolescent youth. Her belief is that mental health issues begin in adolescence and worsen over time if not recognized and treated. She has run several awareness events in our community and around the country and is currently promoting awareness at several Major League baseball stadiums throughout the nation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ELF volunteers get people actively involved in spreading the word that May is mental health awareness month by hi-fiving everyone admitted to the stadium with large foam hands. I remember the first game we attended down with the San Diego Padres. The volunteers were nervous and anxious about how to spread the word. I picked up 2 large foam hands and just started hi-fiving everyone I saw. This became contagious. At the Angels game 2 weeks later, I counted over 10, 000 fans I slapped hands with and over a dozen who made contributions to our foundation. Last year we went to Atlanta and New York and this year Mara is hitting all 5 California Major League stadiums and a minor league stadium in Sacramento. Eventually the goal is to make May as visible as October is for Breast Cancer awareness. Imagine an annual mental health awareness day at every stadium where players dress in green to represent mental health. Wouldn’t that be amazing?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mara has attended several city council committee meetings all over Orange County. Through her efforts several cities have declared May as National Mental Health Awareness Month. This is another step towards helping people recognize that the mental health of the nation is a national emergency and that funding is vitally needed to give sufferers the help they need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mara has written and self-published a children’s book: The Power of Piggie Bear. This is a wonderful, fun and informative book which teaches children (and adults) how to recognize their emotions and then how to control them through 2 simple exercises. First: deep belly breathing (yoga style) and second: a self-hug releasing natural good feeling chemicals through your body. This really works. Like exercise, if you do it every day, you will see a difference. Mara has donated books to all our local elementary and middle schools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can tell, this is a very personal and important topic for me. I encourage an open dialog with my patients andI discuss and offer help when needed. recommend therapy with psychologists, psychiatrists, hypnotherapists, alternative healers, clergy: anyone or any approach that they choose. Many of my patients are surprised when I ask about multiple alternative topics to routine obstetrics and gynecology. Topics including family life, sex, work and of course their own well emotional well-being.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you don’t ask , you will not know and if you don’t know, you can never help guide others to heal. Please speak out. Ask for help. Recognize that others are suffering and offer help. This is our obligation as both healers and human beings. “&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Kenneth James M.D.</name></author><summary type="html">If we are honest, most of us initially feel awkward and anxious when confronted with odd and abnormal behavior. You would think doctors would feel differently, but Kenneth James M.D. candidly admits that he found interaction with psychiatric patients uncomfortable and fear inducing. Dr. James is a board certified Obstetrician and Gynecologist who is married to Mara James, the founder of the Extraordinary Lives Foundation and sits on the Advisory Board. He expresses his fears and feelings on mental health and recounts how experiencing his wife’s personal struggle has made him more understanding and compassionate. “May is Mental Health Awareness month. Five years ago this month my life turned upside down. When I was in medical school, I spent 2 months doing a psychiatric rotation at a V.A. Hospital. This was a requirement. I had no interest in psychiatry and honestly never even thought about mental health disorders before medical school, especially during the first 2 years of school. Sure, I learned about the disorders, neurological pathways, possible causes and pharmacologic treatments but I thought of it as a fiction novel not real disorders that happen to real people. My rotation was during a frigid winter at the V.A. Hospital in Chicago. We were introduced to the in-patient ward staff, instructed on areas to go to and avoid and then assigned our patients to follow. I remember sitting in my first interview with an inpatient. When I arrived at the physician’s consultation room, the patient was already there sitting opposite the doctor. The patient had schizophrenia and was heavily medicated. He seemed harmless, cooperative and sedated. The session lasted 30 minutes with lots of questions about his medical progress, relationship with other patients, satisfaction with his accommodations and goals to accomplish. When we were done, I stood up to say goodbye and open the door for him. When he stood up, I realized he was over 6 feet 10 inches tall and towered over me like a giant. I immediately went into fight or flight mode. I started sweating, was anxious, nervous, fearful and terrified all at the same time. I felt threatened that he was going to lash out at me. There was no basis for this fear. This was a fantasy I immediately fabricated in my mind from watching too many horror movies in the 70’s. He politely grunted goodbye and was escorted back to the common area by a hospital orderly. It was at this exact moment that I realized I would either fear these patients or learn compassion. I chose fear. As the rotation continued, I found myself (and my fellow students) spending more time in the V.A. gymnasium playing basketball than seeing patients. We would study diseases and treatments over breakfast, then play hoops for 2 hours, then lunch and home. I knew the names of all the diseases, symptoms, possible causes and treatment options; I just couldn’t put a face to each disorder because I was afraid of being with people who were psychologically different, diseased or afflicted. Bipolar, schizophrenia, multiple personality disorders and PTSD were cool to talk about and learn the medications that control the symptoms, but to see a person express these disorders live frightened me. Therefore, I avoided patient care for the remainder of my rotation. Sad, but true. My experience in medical school, where it was a requirement to see and interact with psychiatric patients is not that different from any of us who interact with friends, family, neighbors, work mates or strangers who have similar emotional or diagnosed psychiatric conditions. At first it is frightening and uncomfortable. How can someone be there physically but not there mentally or emotionally? It takes time to adjust to and tolerate people with mania, narcissism, or dissociative behavior and to see the real person underneath the disorder. In May of 2014, my wife Mara of over 20 years experienced a manic episode. Looking back, I should have seen it coming like a dark rain cloud before the storm but mostly I just accepted her increasingly bizarre behavior as eccentric. She always had a type A, outgoing and friendly personality. She has always had a lot of friends, been extremely cordial to everyone and made everyone in her presence feel loved and wanted. As her mania slowly progressed, I noticed that many of her friends were not around. Maybe they were growing weary of her changing personality and possibly frightened by her overly talkative behavior and odd mannerisms. Her obsessions with objects, people, and certain situations were bordering on psychiatric and then BAM! I was away the weekend of May 23, 2014 with my parents and brother at a retreat in Colorado. It was one of the few times I had gone away without her. The first night I was gone, she reached the pinnacle of her disease and by the next day I was on a plane home. At 8 pm we embraced. I didn’t want to let her go because I would then have to make some very difficult decisions. With the help of a dear friend who is a psychologist, we decided that she should see her psychologist and a psychiatrist the next day and we would hopefully be able to keep her from being admitted to an inpatient setting. Luckily, with the help of her providers, she was started on medication and started to heal. Over the next 6 months she underwent her own type of transformation. As she proclaims: ‘I went from medication to meditation’. She finished a short course of medications and therapy and then started alternative treatments. Between hypnotherapy, crystals, shamans, yoga, meditation and religious counseling she was transformed. She is back and better than ever! Mara took her experience and decided to help others. She started a mental health awareness foundation called Extraordinary Lives Foundation (ELF) in 2016. The mission of the foundation is to raise awareness around mental health issues concentrating on children and adolescent youth. Her belief is that mental health issues begin in adolescence and worsen over time if not recognized and treated. She has run several awareness events in our community and around the country and is currently promoting awareness at several Major League baseball stadiums throughout the nation. ELF volunteers get people actively involved in spreading the word that May is mental health awareness month by hi-fiving everyone admitted to the stadium with large foam hands. I remember the first game we attended down with the San Diego Padres. The volunteers were nervous and anxious about how to spread the word. I picked up 2 large foam hands and just started hi-fiving everyone I saw. This became contagious. At the Angels game 2 weeks later, I counted over 10, 000 fans I slapped hands with and over a dozen who made contributions to our foundation. Last year we went to Atlanta and New York and this year Mara is hitting all 5 California Major League stadiums and a minor league stadium in Sacramento. Eventually the goal is to make May as visible as October is for Breast Cancer awareness. Imagine an annual mental health awareness day at every stadium where players dress in green to represent mental health. Wouldn’t that be amazing? Mara has attended several city council committee meetings all over Orange County. Through her efforts several cities have declared May as National Mental Health Awareness Month. This is another step towards helping people recognize that the mental health of the nation is a national emergency and that funding is vitally needed to give sufferers the help they need. Mara has written and self-published a children’s book: The Power of Piggie Bear. This is a wonderful, fun and informative book which teaches children (and adults) how to recognize their emotions and then how to control them through 2 simple exercises. First: deep belly breathing (yoga style) and second: a self-hug releasing natural good feeling chemicals through your body. This really works. Like exercise, if you do it every day, you will see a difference. Mara has donated books to all our local elementary and middle schools. As you can tell, this is a very personal and important topic for me. I encourage an open dialog with my patients andI discuss and offer help when needed. recommend therapy with psychologists, psychiatrists, hypnotherapists, alternative healers, clergy: anyone or any approach that they choose. Many of my patients are surprised when I ask about multiple alternative topics to routine obstetrics and gynecology. Topics including family life, sex, work and of course their own well emotional well-being. If you don’t ask , you will not know and if you don’t know, you can never help guide others to heal. Please speak out. Ask for help. Recognize that others are suffering and offer help. This is our obligation as both healers and human beings. “</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.extraordinarylives.us/https://www.extraordinarylives.us/uploads/hands-crossed.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.extraordinarylives.us/https://www.extraordinarylives.us/uploads/hands-crossed.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Need For Electronic Curfews</title><link href="https://www.extraordinarylives.us/https://www.extraordinarylives.us/blog/articles/the-need-for-electronic-curfews" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Need For Electronic Curfews" /><published>2019-06-17T19:36:06-07:00</published><updated>2019-06-17T19:36:06-07:00</updated><id>https://www.extraordinarylives.us/https://www.extraordinarylives.us/blog/articles/the-need-for-electronic-curfews</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.extraordinarylives.us/https://www.extraordinarylives.us/blog/articles/the-need-for-electronic-curfews">&lt;p&gt;A new study in the journal Child Development shows that nighttime use of a cell phone can increase anxiety and depression in teenagers and reduce their self esteem. Although as a parent you may have suspected this, this is the first study that shows a direct link between screen time and mental health. Rates of depression in teenagers have risen over 70% in the last two decades and even in Orange County we have seen a disconcerting number of suicides by young people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sleep is essential for children and teenagers who need 9 hours of sleep per night. Yes - 9 hours. Very difficult to achieve given the early school start times, homework and after school activities and the pressure to achieve and excel. Layer on top of that the fact that, as this new study demonstrates, screen time before bed can seriously disrupt sleep patterns and it is likely that most teenagers are sleep deprived. Lack of sleep can lead to depression, emotional fragility and acting out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The study shows that even if kids are having a great time on their phone, if it disrupts their sleep pattern, then it causes harm. So how can we as parents make sure that our children are not using their phones just before sleep? A difficult proposition given that 50% of teenagers report feeling addicted to their phones and reasoning with teenagers is never easy. Psychologist Lisa Damour offers some practical solutions that offer a starting point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Setting phone boundaries while your children are still young will help with the battle as they get older. Establish good family habits and be a good role model to your children. It is no use telling your children to turn off their phones and limit usage if you as a parent are overusing yours.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Set a central location in the home where all the phones are charged. It may have to be in the parents’ bedroom so your teenagers can’t access their phones after a certain time, though it is not ideal to have any electronic devices in the sleep area.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At the risk of being really unpopular, a digital curfew is essential. Make the curfew universal for everyone in the household. Like most habits, it takes time to establish them, but then they become the norm.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Explain to your teenager that it is your duty as a parent to protect them in the same way as you insist they put on a seat belt before driving in the car, or wearing a helmet while riding a bike.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Make sure that technology and social media do not interfere with the things that promote good health: sleep (9+ hours), personal interaction, physical activity, opportunities to learn and grow.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name>Jane Noble</name></author><summary type="html">A new study in the journal Child Development shows that nighttime use of a cell phone can increase anxiety and depression in teenagers and reduce their self esteem. Although as a parent you may have suspected this, this is the first study that shows a direct link between screen time and mental health. Rates of depression in teenagers have risen over 70% in the last two decades and even in Orange County we have seen a disconcerting number of suicides by young people. Sleep is essential for children and teenagers who need 9 hours of sleep per night. Yes - 9 hours. Very difficult to achieve given the early school start times, homework and after school activities and the pressure to achieve and excel. Layer on top of that the fact that, as this new study demonstrates, screen time before bed can seriously disrupt sleep patterns and it is likely that most teenagers are sleep deprived. Lack of sleep can lead to depression, emotional fragility and acting out. The study shows that even if kids are having a great time on their phone, if it disrupts their sleep pattern, then it causes harm. So how can we as parents make sure that our children are not using their phones just before sleep? A difficult proposition given that 50% of teenagers report feeling addicted to their phones and reasoning with teenagers is never easy. Psychologist Lisa Damour offers some practical solutions that offer a starting point. Setting phone boundaries while your children are still young will help with the battle as they get older. Establish good family habits and be a good role model to your children. It is no use telling your children to turn off their phones and limit usage if you as a parent are overusing yours. Set a central location in the home where all the phones are charged. It may have to be in the parents’ bedroom so your teenagers can’t access their phones after a certain time, though it is not ideal to have any electronic devices in the sleep area. At the risk of being really unpopular, a digital curfew is essential. Make the curfew universal for everyone in the household. Like most habits, it takes time to establish them, but then they become the norm. Explain to your teenager that it is your duty as a parent to protect them in the same way as you insist they put on a seat belt before driving in the car, or wearing a helmet while riding a bike. Make sure that technology and social media do not interfere with the things that promote good health: sleep (9+ hours), personal interaction, physical activity, opportunities to learn and grow.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.extraordinarylives.us/https://www.extraordinarylives.us/uploads/boy-with-phone.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.extraordinarylives.us/https://www.extraordinarylives.us/uploads/boy-with-phone.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Paid Family Leave Could Help Future Generations Thrive</title><link href="https://www.extraordinarylives.us/https://www.extraordinarylives.us/blog/articles/paid-family-leave-could-help-future-generations-thrive" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Paid Family Leave Could Help Future Generations Thrive" /><published>2019-05-19T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2019-05-19T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://www.extraordinarylives.us/https://www.extraordinarylives.us/blog/articles/paid-family-leave-could-help-future-generations-thrive</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.extraordinarylives.us/https://www.extraordinarylives.us/blog/articles/paid-family-leave-could-help-future-generations-thrive">&lt;p&gt;The first few months of a child’s life can have an influence on its future mental health. The baby/mother bond begins as soon as the embryo starts to develop in the womb. The baby experiences life through the mama, hearing the sounds of her body and the steady beat of her heart. By about 26 weeks, the baby starts to react to noises outside the mother’s body and may be soothed by her voice. Fathers and siblings may start the bonding process in many simple ways - talking and singing to the baby, massaging the mother’s belly, feeling the baby kicking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there is nothing quite like the moment when the baby enters the world and becomes a tangible part of the family. The first few weeks and months of a newborn’s life are crucial and can have an influence on the child’s future mental wellbeing. Too often parents do not have have enough time to fully bond and adjust to life with their new addition before having to go back to work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On May 16, 2019, Governor Gavin Newsom convened a Paid Family Leave Task Force for their first in a series of meetings. The Task Force is intended to design a policy and funding roadmap to achieving the Governor’s vision for providing all California newborns with six months of bonding time with their parents. Erin Gabel, Deputy Director of External and Governmental Affairs for First 5 California, was appointed to the newly-established Paid Family Leave Task Force. Erin sees Paid Family Leave during those vitally important first months of a baby’s life, as a developmental necessity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Governor Newsom has appointed a diverse group of representatives from across the state, including members of the business, legal, policy, science, and early learning communities, to put their collective expertise together and design real options to meet the family leave needs of newborns, employers, employees, and their families. The Governor’s goal is to leverage Paid Family Leave to reap greater lifetime benefits for all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Task Force will examine California’s nation-leading Paid Family Leave Program and develop options to increase leave access, provide better job protections, and to expand the length of coverage for California’s workers. Studies have shown that paid family leave allows parents and caregivers to bond with their newborns, and set our littlest community members on a course for better health and greater success in life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Having a Governor who understands the brain science and how Paid Family Leave plays a role in allowing parents the precious time to Talk. Read. Sing. ®with their babies, is a once in a lifetime opportunity,” said Ms. Gabel. “Children and families thriving will help lift all of Californians.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Task Force is due to provide its recommendations to the Governor by the end of 2019.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jane Noble</name></author><summary type="html">The first few months of a child’s life can have an influence on its future mental health. The baby/mother bond begins as soon as the embryo starts to develop in the womb. The baby experiences life through the mama, hearing the sounds of her body and the steady beat of her heart. By about 26 weeks, the baby starts to react to noises outside the mother’s body and may be soothed by her voice. Fathers and siblings may start the bonding process in many simple ways - talking and singing to the baby, massaging the mother’s belly, feeling the baby kicking. But there is nothing quite like the moment when the baby enters the world and becomes a tangible part of the family. The first few weeks and months of a newborn’s life are crucial and can have an influence on the child’s future mental wellbeing. Too often parents do not have have enough time to fully bond and adjust to life with their new addition before having to go back to work. On May 16, 2019, Governor Gavin Newsom convened a Paid Family Leave Task Force for their first in a series of meetings. The Task Force is intended to design a policy and funding roadmap to achieving the Governor’s vision for providing all California newborns with six months of bonding time with their parents. Erin Gabel, Deputy Director of External and Governmental Affairs for First 5 California, was appointed to the newly-established Paid Family Leave Task Force. Erin sees Paid Family Leave during those vitally important first months of a baby’s life, as a developmental necessity. Governor Newsom has appointed a diverse group of representatives from across the state, including members of the business, legal, policy, science, and early learning communities, to put their collective expertise together and design real options to meet the family leave needs of newborns, employers, employees, and their families. The Governor’s goal is to leverage Paid Family Leave to reap greater lifetime benefits for all. The Task Force will examine California’s nation-leading Paid Family Leave Program and develop options to increase leave access, provide better job protections, and to expand the length of coverage for California’s workers. Studies have shown that paid family leave allows parents and caregivers to bond with their newborns, and set our littlest community members on a course for better health and greater success in life. “Having a Governor who understands the brain science and how Paid Family Leave plays a role in allowing parents the precious time to Talk. Read. Sing. ®with their babies, is a once in a lifetime opportunity,” said Ms. Gabel. “Children and families thriving will help lift all of Californians.” The Task Force is due to provide its recommendations to the Governor by the end of 2019.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.extraordinarylives.us/https://www.extraordinarylives.us/uploads/mother-and-child.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.extraordinarylives.us/https://www.extraordinarylives.us/uploads/mother-and-child.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Let Laughter Shed Light</title><link href="https://www.extraordinarylives.us/https://www.extraordinarylives.us/blog/events/let-laughter-shed-light" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Let Laughter Shed Light" /><published>2019-03-14T19:58:18-07:00</published><updated>2019-03-14T19:58:18-07:00</updated><id>https://www.extraordinarylives.us/https://www.extraordinarylives.us/blog/events/let-laughter-shed-light</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.extraordinarylives.us/https://www.extraordinarylives.us/blog/events/let-laughter-shed-light">&lt;p&gt;On Wednesday, February 27, 2019, laughter rang around the Irvine Improv at our first annual Comedy Night entitled Let Laughter Shed Light. Mental illness is no laughing matter, yet love and laughter enable us all to cope better with what life throws at us. There was a wonderful sense of camaraderie at the event and a true feeling that we are all in this together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fun started with guests being enthusiastically greeted by a life size Piggie Bear and volunteers dressed in black with a touch of green to represent mental health. Barely a person passed up the opportunity to pose for a photo with Piggie Bear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;silent-auction&quot;&gt;Silent Auction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once inside, there was a buzz of activity and anticipation as guests perused the many fabulous items on offer in the Silent Auction. There were gifts certificates for yoga, gym memberships, restaurants, the Lakers, singing lessons, golf lessons and massage, as well as for the many wonderful healers that ELF is connected to. The tables were laden with stunning fine jewelry, bubbly and bath products, perfumes, Scotch &amp;amp; chocs to name but a few.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-pre-show&quot;&gt;The Pre-show&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Young performers from the Center Stage Studio warmed up the audience as they shared their talent for singing and dancing in lively routines. Joe Grande, master of ceremonies extraordinaire kept the pace moving with his own inimitable style and good humor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-comedians&quot;&gt;The Comedians&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stand up comedy is not an easy discipline but these professionals had the audience eating out of their hands. First up was Mary Kennedy, best known for “New Fiona” on Shameless, Conan and being a regular at the Laugh Factory in Los Angeles. Mary is hilariously self deprecating as she made fun of her post baby body and had every woman in the room nodding helplessly in agreement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eric Deskin has an edgy, observant brand of humor and the audience lapped up his East Coast take on California. At one point in his life Eric was a lawyer and while rumors of his disbarment have been grossly exaggerated, he advised the audience to ask him for legal advice at their own peril!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Francis DiLorenzo is tall and slender and a magnificent physical comedienne. The laughter built as she told tales of dating shorter men. My personal favorite was her impersonation of her 6’3” son and his similarity to an air filled dancing balloon man. Hilarious!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can see why next up Justine Marino was selected as the New Face of Comedy at Montreal’s prestigious Just for Laughs Festival and laugh we did. Who else do you know who fantasizes about having a Jurassic Park wedding? “I dino…”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To close out the evening Sam Fedele made sure that our jaws ached from laughing. Sam developed his high-energy style of comedy growing up in the mean streets of New Jersey. He spent six years honing his skills in the United States Marine Corps, after which neither Sam nor the Marine Corps would ever be the same again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ELF sends out a huge thank you to all the fabulous entertainers for sharing their talents and shedding light on mental health. The entertainers, guests and volunteers made the evening a spectacular success.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jane Noble</name></author><summary type="html">On Wednesday, February 27, 2019, laughter rang around the Irvine Improv at our first annual Comedy Night entitled Let Laughter Shed Light. Mental illness is no laughing matter, yet love and laughter enable us all to cope better with what life throws at us. There was a wonderful sense of camaraderie at the event and a true feeling that we are all in this together. The fun started with guests being enthusiastically greeted by a life size Piggie Bear and volunteers dressed in black with a touch of green to represent mental health. Barely a person passed up the opportunity to pose for a photo with Piggie Bear. Silent Auction Once inside, there was a buzz of activity and anticipation as guests perused the many fabulous items on offer in the Silent Auction. There were gifts certificates for yoga, gym memberships, restaurants, the Lakers, singing lessons, golf lessons and massage, as well as for the many wonderful healers that ELF is connected to. The tables were laden with stunning fine jewelry, bubbly and bath products, perfumes, Scotch &amp;amp; chocs to name but a few. The Pre-show Young performers from the Center Stage Studio warmed up the audience as they shared their talent for singing and dancing in lively routines. Joe Grande, master of ceremonies extraordinaire kept the pace moving with his own inimitable style and good humor. The Comedians Stand up comedy is not an easy discipline but these professionals had the audience eating out of their hands. First up was Mary Kennedy, best known for “New Fiona” on Shameless, Conan and being a regular at the Laugh Factory in Los Angeles. Mary is hilariously self deprecating as she made fun of her post baby body and had every woman in the room nodding helplessly in agreement. Eric Deskin has an edgy, observant brand of humor and the audience lapped up his East Coast take on California. At one point in his life Eric was a lawyer and while rumors of his disbarment have been grossly exaggerated, he advised the audience to ask him for legal advice at their own peril! Francis DiLorenzo is tall and slender and a magnificent physical comedienne. The laughter built as she told tales of dating shorter men. My personal favorite was her impersonation of her 6’3” son and his similarity to an air filled dancing balloon man. Hilarious! You can see why next up Justine Marino was selected as the New Face of Comedy at Montreal’s prestigious Just for Laughs Festival and laugh we did. Who else do you know who fantasizes about having a Jurassic Park wedding? “I dino…” To close out the evening Sam Fedele made sure that our jaws ached from laughing. Sam developed his high-energy style of comedy growing up in the mean streets of New Jersey. He spent six years honing his skills in the United States Marine Corps, after which neither Sam nor the Marine Corps would ever be the same again. ELF sends out a huge thank you to all the fabulous entertainers for sharing their talents and shedding light on mental health. The entertainers, guests and volunteers made the evening a spectacular success.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.extraordinarylives.us/https://www.extraordinarylives.us/uploads/comedy-night-2019-009-large.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.extraordinarylives.us/https://www.extraordinarylives.us/uploads/comedy-night-2019-009-large.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Staying Sane During The Holidays</title><link href="https://www.extraordinarylives.us/https://www.extraordinarylives.us/blog/press-coverage/staying-sane-during-the-holidays" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Staying Sane During The Holidays" /><published>2018-12-11T18:32:00-08:00</published><updated>2018-12-11T18:32:00-08:00</updated><id>https://www.extraordinarylives.us/https://www.extraordinarylives.us/blog/press-coverage/staying-sane-during-the-holidays</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.extraordinarylives.us/https://www.extraordinarylives.us/blog/press-coverage/staying-sane-during-the-holidays">&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/X3jwcukmUiY&quot; width=&quot;&quot; height=&quot;&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay; fullscreen&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foundation is delighted that CBS News turned to ELF founder, Mara James, to share some tips and advice on how to navigate the holiday season. It is not easy staying sane during the holiday period. It becomes even more difficult for people who have mental health issues. What should be a joyful and exciting time can easily become stressful and filled with anxiety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Piggie Bear was created to help children manage their emotions, yet we as adults can also benefit from Piggie Bear’s teachings. Emotions can be calmed and controlled through deep, belly breathing. If you feel your emotions racing out of control, just take yourself to a quiet place and breathe deeply for 5 minutes. For anyone feel a little sad and lonely, Piggie Bear teaches us to love ourselves and give ourselves a huge hug. Holding that hug can release oxytocin which helps fight off depression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As parents it is important to remember that children are like sponges when it comes to absorbing other people’s emotions. The calmer and happier the parents are, the calmer and more contented the children. Mara reminds everyone that it is more important to spend quality time with family and friends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If sending holiday cards is causing anxiety, then don’t send then. Simplify your life and focus on what is most important.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jane Noble</name></author><summary type="html">The Foundation is delighted that CBS News turned to ELF founder, Mara James, to share some tips and advice on how to navigate the holiday season. It is not easy staying sane during the holiday period. It becomes even more difficult for people who have mental health issues. What should be a joyful and exciting time can easily become stressful and filled with anxiety. Piggie Bear was created to help children manage their emotions, yet we as adults can also benefit from Piggie Bear’s teachings. Emotions can be calmed and controlled through deep, belly breathing. If you feel your emotions racing out of control, just take yourself to a quiet place and breathe deeply for 5 minutes. For anyone feel a little sad and lonely, Piggie Bear teaches us to love ourselves and give ourselves a huge hug. Holding that hug can release oxytocin which helps fight off depression. As parents it is important to remember that children are like sponges when it comes to absorbing other people’s emotions. The calmer and happier the parents are, the calmer and more contented the children. Mara reminds everyone that it is more important to spend quality time with family and friends. If sending holiday cards is causing anxiety, then don’t send then. Simplify your life and focus on what is most important.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.extraordinarylives.us/https://www.extraordinarylives.us/uploads/cbs-elf-appearance.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.extraordinarylives.us/https://www.extraordinarylives.us/uploads/cbs-elf-appearance.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Heads Together: The Duke Of Cambridge Launches ‘Mental Health At Work’</title><link href="https://www.extraordinarylives.us/https://www.extraordinarylives.us/blog/articles/heads-together-the-duke-of-cambridge-launches-mental-health-at-work" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Heads Together: The Duke Of Cambridge Launches 'Mental Health At Work'" /><published>2018-09-11T17:15:00-07:00</published><updated>2018-09-11T17:15:00-07:00</updated><id>https://www.extraordinarylives.us/https://www.extraordinarylives.us/blog/articles/heads-together-the-duke-of-cambridge-launches-mental-health-at-work</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.extraordinarylives.us/https://www.extraordinarylives.us/blog/articles/heads-together-the-duke-of-cambridge-launches-mental-health-at-work">&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/jGlZN58zDnY&quot; width=&quot;&quot; height=&quot;&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay; fullscreen&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In partnership with the mental health charity, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mind.org.uk&quot;&gt;Mind&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.headstogether.org.uk/&quot;&gt;Heads Together&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.royalfoundation.com&quot;&gt;The Royal Foundation&lt;/a&gt; have launched a new online platform, Mental Health at Work, which brings together a wealth of resources, training and information to help people make their life better at work - for themselves, and for their colleagues. No matter the size of your workplace, and no matter where you work, mental health is essential to our daily well being. Mental Health at Work aims to change the way the workplace approaches mental health and eliminate the stigma that accompanies admitting all is not well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is fantastic that The Duke and Duchess of Cambridge, and The Duke of Sussex are highlighting this important subject. Taking care of mental health at work makes sound business sense. It means taking care of a company’s most valuable asset - people - so that they are happy and perform at their best. Having motivated employees is a win-win for employers and customers. It is important to be observant as to how people express their stress and then have sensitive conversations and take appropriate action to ease the situation without fear of discrimination.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jane Noble</name></author><summary type="html">In partnership with the mental health charity, Mind, Heads Together and The Royal Foundation have launched a new online platform, Mental Health at Work, which brings together a wealth of resources, training and information to help people make their life better at work - for themselves, and for their colleagues. No matter the size of your workplace, and no matter where you work, mental health is essential to our daily well being. Mental Health at Work aims to change the way the workplace approaches mental health and eliminate the stigma that accompanies admitting all is not well. It is fantastic that The Duke and Duchess of Cambridge, and The Duke of Sussex are highlighting this important subject. Taking care of mental health at work makes sound business sense. It means taking care of a company’s most valuable asset - people - so that they are happy and perform at their best. Having motivated employees is a win-win for employers and customers. It is important to be observant as to how people express their stress and then have sensitive conversations and take appropriate action to ease the situation without fear of discrimination.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.extraordinarylives.us/https://www.extraordinarylives.us/uploads/heads-together-mental-health-at-work.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.extraordinarylives.us/https://www.extraordinarylives.us/uploads/heads-together-mental-health-at-work.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">CHOC and ELF Go For A Home Run</title><link href="https://www.extraordinarylives.us/https://www.extraordinarylives.us/blog/articles/choc-and-elf-go-for-a-home-run" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="CHOC and ELF Go For A Home Run" /><published>2018-05-20T12:29:57-07:00</published><updated>2018-05-20T12:29:57-07:00</updated><id>https://www.extraordinarylives.us/https://www.extraordinarylives.us/blog/articles/choc-and-elf-go-for-a-home-run</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.extraordinarylives.us/https://www.extraordinarylives.us/blog/articles/choc-and-elf-go-for-a-home-run">&lt;p&gt;It is always so satisfying when you plan for months for an event and it all turns out so well on the day. Many months ago, CHOC Children’s decided to collaborate with ELF to highlight May as Mental Health Awareness Month at the Twins v. Angels game that took place last Saturday evening, May 12 at Angel Stadium. ELF is thrilled that CHOC is leading the way in recognizing that children’s mental health is as important as their physical health. There is no health without mental health.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The day before the game, the wind was whipping up, clouds were hurrying across the sky and much needed rain was watering our gardens. Great, but not what you want for an outdoor event! Saturday could not have been better. The sun shone, families smiled and children laughed. Before the game, it was Angels Fiesta time in the parking lot under the Big A, with mariachi bands sending out strains of salsa that your hips couldn’t resist swaying to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ELF committee members and representatives from CHOC set up shop under a turquoise E-Z Up to welcome guests. Some supporters had purchased their tickets. Other tickets were donated to families at-risk. The message from everyone was as loud and clear as the bright green of our T shirts and sponge hands that popped against the red of the Angels’ fans. High Five for Mental Health! Away with the stigma! We are all in this together! Everyone was having fun high fiving anyone who crossed their path.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The event took place on the day before Mother’s Day and it was wonderful to see so many families with young children and teenagers at the game. You could spot the ELF/CHOC squad from anywhere in the stadium, neon shirts and hats aglow. The only thing that would have improved the evening was a win by the Angels who unfortunately lost to the Minnesota Twins 5:3 in the 12th.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jane Noble</name></author><summary type="html">It is always so satisfying when you plan for months for an event and it all turns out so well on the day. Many months ago, CHOC Children’s decided to collaborate with ELF to highlight May as Mental Health Awareness Month at the Twins v. Angels game that took place last Saturday evening, May 12 at Angel Stadium. ELF is thrilled that CHOC is leading the way in recognizing that children’s mental health is as important as their physical health. There is no health without mental health. The day before the game, the wind was whipping up, clouds were hurrying across the sky and much needed rain was watering our gardens. Great, but not what you want for an outdoor event! Saturday could not have been better. The sun shone, families smiled and children laughed. Before the game, it was Angels Fiesta time in the parking lot under the Big A, with mariachi bands sending out strains of salsa that your hips couldn’t resist swaying to. ELF committee members and representatives from CHOC set up shop under a turquoise E-Z Up to welcome guests. Some supporters had purchased their tickets. Other tickets were donated to families at-risk. The message from everyone was as loud and clear as the bright green of our T shirts and sponge hands that popped against the red of the Angels’ fans. High Five for Mental Health! Away with the stigma! We are all in this together! Everyone was having fun high fiving anyone who crossed their path. The event took place on the day before Mother’s Day and it was wonderful to see so many families with young children and teenagers at the game. You could spot the ELF/CHOC squad from anywhere in the stadium, neon shirts and hats aglow. The only thing that would have improved the evening was a win by the Angels who unfortunately lost to the Minnesota Twins 5:3 in the 12th.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.extraordinarylives.us/https://www.extraordinarylives.us/uploads/twins-vs-angels-2018-05-12-003-large.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.extraordinarylives.us/https://www.extraordinarylives.us/uploads/twins-vs-angels-2018-05-12-003-large.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">ELF Goes National!</title><link href="https://www.extraordinarylives.us/https://www.extraordinarylives.us/blog/events/elf-goes-national" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ELF Goes National!" /><published>2018-05-16T20:27:00-07:00</published><updated>2018-05-16T20:27:00-07:00</updated><id>https://www.extraordinarylives.us/https://www.extraordinarylives.us/blog/events/elf-goes-national</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.extraordinarylives.us/https://www.extraordinarylives.us/blog/events/elf-goes-national">&lt;p&gt;Wow! It is hard to believe that this is our second year hosting Mental Health Awareness Events at MLB stadiums and we have already gone national! This was not part of the original plan but when I received notification of a suicide in New York and another one in Atlanta, I felt compelled to take action. I have family and friends in both locations so knew we could make something happen. I got on the phone with the NY Yankees and Atlanta Braves and they were both on board with helping up host an event. We were at SunTrust Park on May 4th and Yankee Stadium on May 6.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The energy at both stadiums was amazing! There were only 50 of us at each game, but our enthusiasm made up for numbers and I know that we made a BIG impact in bringing awareness to May as National Mental Health Awareness Month. You couldn’t miss us with with our large, fun sponge hands along with our neon green ELF hats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I owe my hubby a big thank you for all of his support in my endeavors and for being the BEST high-fiver I could ever ask for. I would also like to thank our sponsors and my friends for donating to my birthday fundraiser which paid for at-risk children and their families to attend our events.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Mara James</name></author><summary type="html">Wow! It is hard to believe that this is our second year hosting Mental Health Awareness Events at MLB stadiums and we have already gone national! This was not part of the original plan but when I received notification of a suicide in New York and another one in Atlanta, I felt compelled to take action. I have family and friends in both locations so knew we could make something happen. I got on the phone with the NY Yankees and Atlanta Braves and they were both on board with helping up host an event. We were at SunTrust Park on May 4th and Yankee Stadium on May 6. The energy at both stadiums was amazing! There were only 50 of us at each game, but our enthusiasm made up for numbers and I know that we made a BIG impact in bringing awareness to May as National Mental Health Awareness Month. You couldn’t miss us with with our large, fun sponge hands along with our neon green ELF hats. I owe my hubby a big thank you for all of his support in my endeavors and for being the BEST high-fiver I could ever ask for. I would also like to thank our sponsors and my friends for donating to my birthday fundraiser which paid for at-risk children and their families to attend our events.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.extraordinarylives.us/https://www.extraordinarylives.us/uploads/indians-vs-yankees-2019-05-06-003-large.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.extraordinarylives.us/https://www.extraordinarylives.us/uploads/indians-vs-yankees-2019-05-06-003-large.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">WOW The Wonder Of Women</title><link href="https://www.extraordinarylives.us/https://www.extraordinarylives.us/blog/articles/wow-the-wonder-of-women" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="WOW The Wonder Of Women" /><published>2018-05-08T17:46:12-07:00</published><updated>2018-05-08T17:46:12-07:00</updated><id>https://www.extraordinarylives.us/https://www.extraordinarylives.us/blog/articles/wow-the-wonder-of-women</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.extraordinarylives.us/https://www.extraordinarylives.us/blog/articles/wow-the-wonder-of-women">&lt;p&gt;WOW is the perfect acronym for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.semel.ucla.edu/wow/WOW-Index.html&quot;&gt;The Wonder of Women Summit&lt;/a&gt; that was held on May 2, 2018 in Los Angeles on the UCLA campus. WOW seemed the perfect response when looking at some of the most successful and influential women of our time coming together to unite in their common goal of promoting a better understanding, awareness and treatment of mental illness in our society. There was a huge amount of talent in one place with featured speakers including Tipper Gore, Lisa Kudrow, Goldie Hawn, Candice Bergen, Dr. Robin Berman, Susan Bookheimer Ph.D., Poppy Jamie and psychic medium Amanda Daniels to name just a few. The full speaker list and more details about the event can be found at https://www.semel.ucla.edu/wow/&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mara James, founder of ELF had the opportunity to chat with Tipper Gore about their common commitment to changing lives for the better. Tipper is a tireless advocate for homelessness and issues of mental health. She is committed to eradicating the stigma and educating Americans on the need for quality, affordable mental health care. During her husband’s tenure as Vice President, she served as the Mental Health Policy Advisor to President Clinton. A genuine trailblazer, Tipper chaired the first White House Conference on Mental Health in 1999 that interactively involved tens of thousands of Americans across the country. She is innovative and courageous, always seeking new ways to raise awareness and promote action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What was so inspiring about the conference was the powerful message that the way we we approach mental health has to change and the determination of these extraordinary women to make it happen.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jane Noble</name></author><summary type="html">WOW is the perfect acronym for The Wonder of Women Summit that was held on May 2, 2018 in Los Angeles on the UCLA campus. WOW seemed the perfect response when looking at some of the most successful and influential women of our time coming together to unite in their common goal of promoting a better understanding, awareness and treatment of mental illness in our society. There was a huge amount of talent in one place with featured speakers including Tipper Gore, Lisa Kudrow, Goldie Hawn, Candice Bergen, Dr. Robin Berman, Susan Bookheimer Ph.D., Poppy Jamie and psychic medium Amanda Daniels to name just a few. The full speaker list and more details about the event can be found at https://www.semel.ucla.edu/wow/ Mara James, founder of ELF had the opportunity to chat with Tipper Gore about their common commitment to changing lives for the better. Tipper is a tireless advocate for homelessness and issues of mental health. She is committed to eradicating the stigma and educating Americans on the need for quality, affordable mental health care. During her husband’s tenure as Vice President, she served as the Mental Health Policy Advisor to President Clinton. A genuine trailblazer, Tipper chaired the first White House Conference on Mental Health in 1999 that interactively involved tens of thousands of Americans across the country. She is innovative and courageous, always seeking new ways to raise awareness and promote action. What was so inspiring about the conference was the powerful message that the way we we approach mental health has to change and the determination of these extraordinary women to make it happen.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.extraordinarylives.us/https://www.extraordinarylives.us/uploads/mara-with-tipper-gore.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.extraordinarylives.us/https://www.extraordinarylives.us/uploads/mara-with-tipper-gore.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Google Values Emotional Intelligence</title><link href="https://www.extraordinarylives.us/https://www.extraordinarylives.us/blog/articles/google-values-emotional-intelligence" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Google Values Emotional Intelligence" /><published>2018-03-27T21:28:50-07:00</published><updated>2018-03-27T21:28:50-07:00</updated><id>https://www.extraordinarylives.us/https://www.extraordinarylives.us/blog/articles/google-values-emotional-intelligence</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.extraordinarylives.us/https://www.extraordinarylives.us/blog/articles/google-values-emotional-intelligence">&lt;p&gt;At ELF we believe wholeheartedly in the need to develop the Emotional Intelligence of young children. Emotional intelligence is the ability to identify and manage one’s own emotions, as well as the emotions of others. Children who are emotionally intelligent are able to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;recognize their own emotions and those of othersdiscern between different feelings and name them appropriatelyuse emotional information to guide thinking, problem solving and behaviorbe able to manage their emotions and adapt to changing environments&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Traits of people who have well developed high emotional intelligence include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;being positive.choosing to be friends with other positive people.setting healthy boundaries.being assertive when necessarynot dwelling on the past.knowing how to enjoy the moment and deal with disappointmentsdescribing themselves as happy.empathizing with others.knowing when to say yes or no in situations&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are all qualities that can help children become confident, discerning and socially strong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you teach children emotional intelligence, how to recognize their feelings, understand where they come from and learn how to deal with them, you teach them one of the most essential skills for their success in life. Research has shown that Emotional Intelligence predicts over 54% of the variation in success for relationships, effectiveness, health and quality of life. Additional data concludes that young people with high EQ earn higher grades, stay in school and make healthier choices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Google it appears also looks for people with well developed emotional intelligence in its hiring process. High test results in STEM subjects (Science, Technology, Engineering &amp;amp; Math) are not enough on their own.Google wants to know if potential employees are able to connect with others, recognize other people’s thoughts and feelings, read situations and people and respond accordingly. The Washington Post recently reported that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The seven top characteristics of success at Google are all soft skills: being a good coach; communicating and listening well; possessing insights into others (including others different values and points of view); having empathy toward and being supportive of one’s colleagues; being a good critical thinker and problem solver; and being able to make connections across complex ideas.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By developing Emotional Intelligence in children at a young age, we can set them on a path to success in all aspects of their lives. Piggie Bear. ELF’s first therapeutic tool, can teach even very young children how to love and accept themselves as they are and not judge others, how to recognize emotions and be empathetic and provide strategies for dealing with emotions before they spiral out of control. It is time for schools to also recognize the importance of these so called “soft skills” that are not easy to develop and are currently being neglected.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jane Noble</name></author><summary type="html">At ELF we believe wholeheartedly in the need to develop the Emotional Intelligence of young children. Emotional intelligence is the ability to identify and manage one’s own emotions, as well as the emotions of others. Children who are emotionally intelligent are able to: recognize their own emotions and those of othersdiscern between different feelings and name them appropriatelyuse emotional information to guide thinking, problem solving and behaviorbe able to manage their emotions and adapt to changing environments Traits of people who have well developed high emotional intelligence include: being positive.choosing to be friends with other positive people.setting healthy boundaries.being assertive when necessarynot dwelling on the past.knowing how to enjoy the moment and deal with disappointmentsdescribing themselves as happy.empathizing with others.knowing when to say yes or no in situations These are all qualities that can help children become confident, discerning and socially strong. When you teach children emotional intelligence, how to recognize their feelings, understand where they come from and learn how to deal with them, you teach them one of the most essential skills for their success in life. Research has shown that Emotional Intelligence predicts over 54% of the variation in success for relationships, effectiveness, health and quality of life. Additional data concludes that young people with high EQ earn higher grades, stay in school and make healthier choices. Google it appears also looks for people with well developed emotional intelligence in its hiring process. High test results in STEM subjects (Science, Technology, Engineering &amp;amp; Math) are not enough on their own.Google wants to know if potential employees are able to connect with others, recognize other people’s thoughts and feelings, read situations and people and respond accordingly. The Washington Post recently reported that: “The seven top characteristics of success at Google are all soft skills: being a good coach; communicating and listening well; possessing insights into others (including others different values and points of view); having empathy toward and being supportive of one’s colleagues; being a good critical thinker and problem solver; and being able to make connections across complex ideas.” By developing Emotional Intelligence in children at a young age, we can set them on a path to success in all aspects of their lives. Piggie Bear. ELF’s first therapeutic tool, can teach even very young children how to love and accept themselves as they are and not judge others, how to recognize emotions and be empathetic and provide strategies for dealing with emotions before they spiral out of control. It is time for schools to also recognize the importance of these so called “soft skills” that are not easy to develop and are currently being neglected.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.extraordinarylives.us/https://www.extraordinarylives.us/uploads/google-headquarters.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.extraordinarylives.us/https://www.extraordinarylives.us/uploads/google-headquarters.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>